Guide to the New York University Department of History Oral History Class Collection OH.033
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York University Department of History Oral History Class Collection
1984-1999
1991-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York University. Department of History
Henry Street Settlement (New York, N.Y.)
Lower East Side Tenement Museum
Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring
Bernhardt, Debra E.
OH.033
5230
10.25 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 5 media boxes, 3 half manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, and 10 card catalog drawers
1.25 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 2 half manuscript boxes
2 videocassettes (vhs)
5 videocassettes (hi8)
239 sound discs (cd)
7 videodiscs (dvd)
203 audiocassettes
The New York University (NYU) Department of History Oral History Class Collection contains over 180 sound and video interviews conducted by graduate students from the NYU Department of History in 1984, between 1991 and 1995, in 1999, and by volunteers from the Workmen's Circle in Manhattan, New York in 1993. The majority of the narrators lived in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Other narrators include residents of the East Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan; members of the Three Arrows Cooperative Society in Putnam Valley, New York; veterans of the Vietnam War; and jazz musicians in New York City between 1940 and 1960. The narrators reflect the changing ethnic composition of different neighborhoods in New York City, and include Jewish immigrants from Eastern Europe; immigrants from Africa, Asia, the Caribbean, and Central America; and migrants from the southern United States and Puerto Rico. Topics covered by the interviews include life in tenements in the LES, life in public and cooperative housing in the LES, family life, ethnic identities, intercultural and interracial relations in New York City, education, religion, paid and unpaid work, immigration and migration experiences, religious and social activities in East Harlem, Asian American activism, socialist and anarchist organizations, political activism, anti-war movements, community gardens in New York City, and experiences of women in higher education through the 1970s and 1990s. In addition to the interviews, the collection includes transcripts (full and partial) of interviews, notes on and indexes of interviews, field notes taken by interviewers, and preliminary questionnaires completed by narrators. Some files include articles and ephemera created by the narrators or are related to the topics they discussed in the interviews.
Conditions Governing Access
The majority of the interviews in this collection are open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The interviews conducted between 1991 and 1993 were donated by Rachel Bernstein in 1993; additional interviews were deposited with the library as classes were completed. The accession numbers related to these gifts are 1950.077 and 2014.143.
Existence and Location of Copies
Many of the interviews in this collection can also be found in Series 8 of the Henry Street Settlement records (sw0058) at the University of Minnesota's Social Welfare History Archives, and at the Lower East Side Tenement Museum.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series, with the first series containing materials created by the oral history classes that participated in the Lower East Side Oral History Project. The remaining series contain materials created by a single oral history class.
The series are as follows:
Series I. Lower East Side Oral History Project Interviews, 1991-1994 Series II. 1995 Oral History Class Interviews, 1995 Series III. 1984 Oral History Class Interview, 1984 Series IV. 1999 Oral History Class Interviews, 1999
Historical Note
The interviews in the New York University Department of History Oral History Class Collection were conducted by graduate students in oral history classes taught by Rachel Bernstein in 1984, between 1991 and 1995, in 1999, and volunteers from the Workmen's Circle in Manhattan, who were trained by Bernstein in two day-long seminars in 1993. The majority of the interviews were conducted as part of the Lower East Side Oral History Project between 1991 and 1994.
Related Materials
The Henry Street Settlement records (sw0058) at the University of Minnesota's Social Welfare History Archives contains unique interviews from the Lower East Side Oral History Project.
Scope and Contents
The New York University (NYU) Department of History Oral History Class Collection contains over 180 sound and video interviews conducted by graduate students from the NYU Department of History between 1991 and 1995, and by volunteers from the Workmen's Circle in Manhattan, New York in 1993. The majority of the narrators lived in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Other narrators lived in the East Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan or were members of the Asian American political movements or the Three Arrows Cooperative Society in Putnam Valley, New York. The narrators reflect the changing ethnic composition of different neighborhoods in New York City, and include Jewish immigrants from Eastern Europe; immigrants from Africa, Asia, the Caribbean, and Central America; and migrants from the southern United States and Puerto Rico. Topics covered by the interviews include life in tenements in the LES, life in public and cooperative housing in the LES, family life, ethnic identities, intercultural and interracial relations in New York City, education, religion, paid and unpaid work, immigration and migration experiences, religious and social activities in East Harlem, Asian American activism, socialist and anarchist organizations, and political activism. In addition to the interviews, the collection includes transcripts (full and partial) of interviews, notes on and indexes of interviews, field notes taken by interviewers, and preliminary questionnaires completed by narrators. Some files include articles and ephemera created by the narrators or are related to the topics they discussed in the interviews.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Tenement houses -- New York (State) -- New York.; Social settlements -- New York (State) -- New York.; Jews -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Social conditions.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Economic conditions.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Ethnic relations.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Housing -- New York (State) -- New York; East Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- History -- 20th century.; Public housing -- New York (State) -- New York; Oral histories (document genres); Transcripts.; Asian Americans -- New York (State) -- New York.; Family-owned business enterprises -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor -- New York (State) -- New York.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Veterans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews.; Jazz musicians -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews.; Community gardens -- New York (State) -- New York.; Peace movements -- United States.; Women in higher education.; Bernhardt, Debra E.
- Series I. Lower East Side Oral History Project Interviews, 1991-1994; 7 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 4 media boxes, and 8 card catalog drawers; 0.75 Linear Feet in one record carton; 4 videocassettes (hi8); 4 videodiscs (dvd); 192 sound discs (cd); 133 audiocassettes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains interviews conducted between 1991 and 1994 as part of the Lower East Side Oral History Project. The interviews document life and work in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York throughout the 20th century. The narrators lived and worked in the LES between the 1910s and 1990s and are mainly Jewish first-generation Americans of Eastern European descent. Other narrators include immigrants and children of immigrants from Eastern Europe, Ireland, and Italy; African-American migrants and children of migrants from the southern United States; and a child of migrants from Puerto Rico.
  The interviews include descriptions of apartments in tenements and public housing and neighborhoods in the LES, discussions of single and dual parent households and divorce in the early 20th century, and relations between Jewish residents of the LES with other ethnic and religious groups in the neighborhood. Narrators discuss social and leisure activities in the LES, including the Yiddish theatre, and discuss the importance of the settlement houses to residents of the LES. Narrators describe paid and unpaid work inside and outside of the home, immigration and migration experiences, labor union activity, and political activism. Many of the interviews contain discussions surrounding Jewish identity in terms of religious and cultural traditions, in particular narrators comparing their experiences as first-generation Americans with their parents' experiences as immigrants.
  The interviews conducted in 1991 focus on the Henry Street Settlement in the LES. The narrators were staff, board members, teachers and former students of the Music School, participants in the Home Planning Workshop, and members of the Henry Street Oldtimers. These interviews cover a wide range of topics relating to the Settlement and the LES, with the majority focusing on the narrators' memories of staff, programs, activities, and events at the Settlement between the 1910s and the 1940s and the importance of the Settlement to the residents of the LES. Many of the narrators discuss their memories of Helen Hall, the director of the Settlement between 1933 and 1967. The narrators include early residents of the Vladeck Houses in the LES who compare the apartments as they were in 1940 and at the time of the interview.
  The interviews conducted in 1993 focus on life in the tenements in the LES between the 1910s and the 1930s. The interviews include vivid descriptions of the layouts of the apartments and living arrangements within them. Narrators describe the neighborhoods and stores in the LES and discuss education and social activities in the LES.
  In addition to the interviews, this series includes transcripts (full and partial) of interviews, notes on and indexes of interviews, field notes taken by interviewers, and preliminary questionnaires completed by narrators.
  Historical Note
  The Lower East Side Oral History Project was undertaken between 1991 and 1994 to document life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Graduate students enrolled in the oral history classes taught by Rachel Bernstein in the New York University Department of History collaborated with the Tenement Museum, Henry Street Settlement House, and the Workmen's Circle in Manhattan to collect interviews with people who lived in the LES between the 1910s and 1990s. Most of the interviews were conducted by graduate students in Bernstein's classes with some interviews conducted in 1993 by volunteers from the Workmen's Circle, who were trained by Bernstein in two day-long seminars. The interviews conducted by the Workmen's Circle volunteers were used in planning the design of the Tenement Museum at 97 Orchard Street in the LES.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by last name of narrator.
  - Arinberg, Pauline, 1993 May 21; 478482 (Box 1, Folder 1, Box 15, Cassette 115, Box 6, Cd 18)
    Biographical Note
    Pauline Arinberg was born in the early 20th century in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she was an only child. Her father immigrated to the United States (US) from Russia in the 1890s and worked in the garment industry, owned a grocery store and a trimming store, and peddled textiles. Her mother immigrated to the US from the Lithuanian region of Russia in the 1890s and worked in a cigar factory and peddled textiles. Arinberg attended Seward Park High School in the LES and Baruch College. She worked as a legal secretary.
    This interview was conducted on May 21, 1993 by Helen Kugler in the Long Island City neighborhood of Queens, New York. The interview covers Pauline Arinberg's early life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and her family. Arinberg discusses the different apartments in which her family lived in the LES and the fact that the family would move to obtain lower rent. She discusses her parents, their backgrounds, and their immigration to the United States. She recounts her father's various occupations, including his trimming store on Christie Street in the LES and his business peddling textiles. She discusses her mother's occupations as a finisher in the garment industry and as a peddler of house dresses and aprons. She describes the apartments in which her family lived, particularly the cold and her loneliness after school when her parents were at work. She discusses ethnic and racial relations in the LES from the early 20th century to the time of the interview. She recounts going to Central Park in Manhattan, Prospect Park in Brooklyn, and the Yiddish theatre with her mother, and other leisure activities in which she participated. Other topics include burglaries that took place in her family's apartments, her religious upbringing, and living conditions in the buildings in which her family lived in the LES.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Duration: 1:34:40
  - Auerbach, Ottile, 1992 October 17; 478556 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Ottile Auerbach was born in 1898 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her parents immigrated to the United States from Russia. Her father owned an unspecified factory. When Auerbach was two years old, her family moved to the Bronx. Her mother died in 1915. She worked as a dietician at the City and Country School in the Greenwich Village neighborhood of Manhattan. She married twice and had at least one child.
    This interview was conducted on October 17, 1992 by Helen Selsdon at an unspecified location. The audio recording for this interview is missing. The interview covers Ottile Auerbach's life in New York, New York and her family. Auerbach discusses her family, her parents' relationship, and her father's factory. She recounts her dislike of her father, mainly due to his frugality. She describes her mother's funeral and burial. She discusses her relationship with her two husbands and her son form her first marriage. She discusses her work as a dietician at the City and Country School in the Greenwich Village neighborhood of Manhattan.
  - Barkin, Dolly Kaminsky, 1993 July 22; 478410 (Box 12, Cassette 43, Box 1, Folder 3, Box 4, Cd 13)
    Dolly Kaminsky Barkin was born in 1929 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and was an only child. Her family was Jewish. Her father immigrated to the United States from Russia and worked as an undertaker. Her mother was born in Hoboken, New Jersey and worked as a machine operator in a garment factory. Her parents divorced when she was in elementary school. Barkin attended Public Schools 91 and 92 and Seward Park High School in the LES. She worked as a bookkeeper in a bank. She married in 1949 and had two children.
    This interview was conducted on July 22, 1993 by Helen Goodman at Dolly Kaminsky Barkin's apartment in Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Barkin's childhood in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, her family, and her experiences at settlement houses in the LES. Barkin recounts her memories of life in the LES in the 1930s and 1940s, describes her family's apartment on Willett Street, and the apartment in the LES she shared with her mother after her parents' divorce. She discusses her parents' divorce and her relationship with her parents after their divorce. She describes her parents' occupations, her mother's work as a machine operator, and her father's work as an undertaker. Barkin describes her mother's family, the family's opinion of her father, and Barkin's estrangement from them. She discusses the importance of the LES settlement houses to her and her friends and her memberships in the Educational Alliance, Madison House, Stanton Street Settlement, Christodora House, University Settlement, and Lavenberg House. She recounts attending dances at all of the settlements and after-school activities at the University Settlement and the Educational Alliance. She discusses meeting her husband, her reasons for marrying him, and his occupations.
    Duration: 56:10
  - Barlow, Mildred, 1991 October 17; 478388 (Box 11, Cassette 18, Box 1, Folder 4, Box 3, Folder 26)
    Mildred Barlow was born into a Jewish family in 1921 in Newark, New Jersey. She had one brother, who had cerebral palsy. When she seven years old, her family moved to the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She moved into the Vladeck Houses in the LES in 1941 with her mother and brother and attended Public School 134. She married and had two children. She separated from her husband when her children were young.
    This interview was conducted by Ulrike Daehnhardt on October 17, 1991 at the Henry Street Settlement's Home Planning Workshop at the Vladeck Houses in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Mildred Barlow's childhood, her family, and her experiences in the Vladeck Houses in the LES. Barlow often switches from topics with little transition. She discusses her childhood, including apartments in which her family lived and food she would buy. She recalls the deaths of her father and her brother. She discusses her separation from her husband and her relationship with her children.
    Duration: 56:00
  - Baron, Samuel, 1991 December 13; 478389 (Box 11, Cassette 19A-19B, Box 1, Folder 5, Box 3, Cd 27-28)
    Samuel Baron was born in 1925 in New York. He was one of three children and his family was Jewish. The family lived in the Bensonhurst neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. His father immigrated to the United States (US) from Russia in 1908 and worked as butcher. His mother immigrated to the US from Poland around 1913 and managed the household. Baron graduated from New Utrecht High School in Brooklyn when he was 14 years old and attended Brooklyn College. He studied violin between ages 8 and 13, before deciding to study the flute when he was thirteen years old. He studied and taught flute at the Music School at the Henry Street Settlement in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan and the Juilliard School in Manhattan. He married and had two children.
    This interview was conducted on December 13, 1991 by Renee Newman at the Juilliard School in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Samuel Baron's experiences at the Music School at the Henry Street Settlement the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. Baron discusses his education and his decision to start studying the flute. He recounts his decision to attend the Music School at the Henry Street Settlement and describes his experience there, including his teachers, the other students, and the orchestra. He recounts attending the Juilliard School and teaching at the Henry Street Settlement. He discusses the people with whom he worked at the Henry Street Settlement, in particular Grace Spofford, Robert Scholz, and Ivan Galamian. He discusses his students at the Henry Street Settlement and his teaching philosophy. Other topics related to the Music School at the Henry Street Settlement include the changes in the ethnic demographics of the students between the 1940s and at the time of the interview and Rosemary Younker's patronage of the Music School. For more interviews about the Music School at the Henry Street Settlement see Behrend, Louise; Canin, Martin; and Herman, David.
    Duration: 1:54:45
    Flute -- Instruction and study -- New York (State) -- New York.; Flute teachers -- United States -- Interviews.; Juilliard School; Spofford, Grace; Galamian, Ivan; Scholz, Robert, 1902-1986
  - Beck, Bertram, 1991 November 14; 478390 (Box 1, Folder 6, Box 11, Cassette 20, Box 3, Cd 29)
    Bertram Beck was born in 1918 in the Rockaway neighborhood of Queens, New York. He had two sisters. He attended Antioch College in Ohio and the University of Chicago in Illinois. He was the Associate Director of the National Association of Social Workers from 1955 to 1960. He was the Executive Director of the Mobilization for Youth in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan from 1965 to 1969 and the Director of the Henry Street Settlement in the LES between 1967 and 1977. At the time of the interview, he was the Dean of the School of Social Work at Fordham University in the Bronx.
    This interview was conducted by Greg Raynor on November 14, 1991 at Bertram Beck's office at Fordham University in the Bronx, New York. The interview covers Beck's experiences as the Director of the Henry Street Settlement in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and as Executive Director at the Mobilization for Youth in the LES. Beck discusses his education and his family, including his work in the Merchant Marine before entering college and his parents' involvement with the Henry Street Settlement. He discusses his cooperative jobs while a student at Antioch College in Ohio and the fact that these led to his interest in social work. He describes the youth development programs at the Settlement and recounts the creation and mission of Mobilization for Youth. He discusses Helen Hall, her philosophy of social work, and her involvement in the creation of Mobilization for Youth. He recounts a strike by Settlement staff in 1965 and the division this led to between the Settlement, Mobilization for Youth, and other organizations in the LES. He describes the differing approaches to social work between the Settlement and Mobilization for Youth and the communities each served. He recounts becoming the Director at the Settlement and issues he faced directing both the Settlement and Mobilization for Youth. He compares his relationship with Helen Hall with her relationship with Lillian Wald. Other topics include Beck's experiences on an unspecified New York City school board and ethnic and racial tensions in the LES. For more interviews with employees of the Henry Street Settlement, see Gold, Leona; McGee-Robinson, Audrey Peters; O'Malley, Nora.
    Duration: 1:17:30
    Mobilization for Youth; Hall, Helen
  - Behar, Albert, 1993 May 22; 478557 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Albert Behar was born in 1914 in the Lower East Side Neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His family was Jewish and he had four siblings. His parents immigrated to the United States from Turkey. His father owned a variety store and his mother managed the household. Behar worked as a sales representative.